<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Notes from the Edge: A Trader's Guide to Mastering the Inner Game on Notes</title><link>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/</link><description>Recent content in Notes from the Edge: A Trader's Guide to Mastering the Inner Game on Notes</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://anas1412.github.io/notes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Introduction: The Rider's Quest to the Edge</title><link>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/00-introduction-the-riders-quest-to-the-edge/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/00-introduction-the-riders-quest-to-the-edge/</guid><description>&lt;p>Greetings, Seeker. You embark on a journey, much like a rider on a quest, seeking truths beyond the familiar horizon. These are &amp;lsquo;Notes from the Edge&amp;rsquo;—insights gleaned from venturing beyond the well-trodden paths of conventional wisdom. This collection challenges ingrained beliefs and offers a transformative path to profound and sustainable fulfillment. We will explore fundamental paradigms that govern our pursuit of goals: Have-Do-Be, Do-Have-Be, and the ultimate destination, the Be-Do-Have.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>1. The Man and His Horse: An Analogy for Mind and Body</title><link>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/01-the-man-and-his-horse/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/01-the-man-and-his-horse/</guid><description>&lt;p>Before we explore these paradigms, let&amp;rsquo;s consider a powerful analogy that will help illuminate the dynamics at play within ourselves: the man and his horse. Imagine you are a rider, and your body is a magnificent, powerful horse.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;The body is the instrument of our soul, and the mind is its conductor.&amp;rdquo;
— B.K.S. Iyengar&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The Man (Your Mind): The rider represents your conscious mind. He is the strategist, the planner, the one who understands maps and directions. He thinks in concepts, recognizes patterns, and can process information at incredible speeds. He can envision distant goals and devise complex routes to reach them. He is fast, analytical, and driven by purpose.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Horse (Your Body): The horse represents your physical body and its subconscious processes. It is powerful and capable, but it understands through feelings, sensations, and repetition. It thrives on comfort, seeks familiar paths, and can be resistant to change. It learns through consistent training and habit, not through abstract thought. The horse is slow to change its ways, but once a habit is ingrained, it can carry you forward with immense momentum.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>For true progress, the man and the horse must work in harmony. A rider who constantly battles his horse, or one who lets the horse wander aimlessly, will never reach his destination efficiently. The man must guide with clear intent, and the horse must be trained to follow, even when the path is unfamiliar or uncomfortable. Throughout this message, keep this analogy in mind, as it will help you understand the interplay between your conscious intentions and your ingrained patterns.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>2. Shadow Work: Making the Unconscious Conscious</title><link>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/02-shadow-work/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/02-shadow-work/</guid><description>&lt;p>The psychologist Carl Jung introduced a profound concept for self-mastery: the Shadow. The Shadow is the part of our unconscious mind that contains all the traits, impulses, and desires we repress or deny—the aspects of ourselves we deem unacceptable. Engaging in Shadow Work is the courageous process of bringing these hidden elements into conscious awareness, not to eliminate them, but to understand and integrate them.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Until you make the unconscious conscious, it will direct your life and you will call it fate.&amp;rdquo;
— Carl Jung&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>3. The Have-Do-Be Model: The Illusion of External Success</title><link>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/03-have-do-be-model/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/03-have-do-be-model/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is the most common, yet often least effective, approach. In the Have-Do-Be model, people believe they first need to have something (e.g., a degree, money, a specific relationship) in order to do something (e.g., get a good job, start a business, be happy), which then allows them to be a certain way (e.g., successful, fulfilled, loved).&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;If only I had X, then I could do Y, and then I would be Z.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>4. The Do-Have-Be Model: The Treadmill of Action</title><link>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/04-do-have-be-model/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/04-do-have-be-model/</guid><description>&lt;p>A slight improvement, the Do-Have-Be model focuses on action. Here, individuals believe they must first do something (e.g., work hard, hustle relentlessly, network constantly) to have something (e.g., a promotion, wealth, recognition), which then allows them to be a certain way (e.g., respected, powerful, secure). This model is heavily promoted in professional life and the hustle culture.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;I will do everything it takes to have success, so I can finally be happy.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>5. The Power of Self-Image: Who You Believe You Are</title><link>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/05-power-of-self-image/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/05-power-of-self-image/</guid><description>&lt;p>Before we delve into the transformative Be-Do-Have model, it&amp;rsquo;s crucial to understand the foundational role of your self-image. Your self-image is the mental picture you have of yourself – your beliefs about who you are, what you&amp;rsquo;re capable of, and what you deserve. It&amp;rsquo;s the blueprint that dictates your actions and ultimately, your results.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Man cannot consistently act beyond what he believes himself to be.&amp;rdquo;
— Maxwell Maltz, Psycho-Cybernetics&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>If you perceive yourself as incapable, unworthy, or unlucky, your actions will unconsciously align with that belief, creating a self-fulfilling prophecy. Conversely, a strong, positive self-image empowers you to take bold actions and persist through challenges, because you inherently believe in your capacity to succeed. Cultivating a healthy self-image is the first step towards truly embodying the &amp;lsquo;Be&amp;rsquo; in the Be-Do-Have model. It&amp;rsquo;s like the rider clearly visualizing the horse&amp;rsquo;s strength and capability, and the horse, in turn, sensing the rider&amp;rsquo;s confidence and responding in kind.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>6. The Dunning-Kruger Effect: The Peak of "Mount Stupid"</title><link>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/06-dunning-kruger-effect/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/06-dunning-kruger-effect/</guid><description>&lt;p>As we explore the power of self-image, we must also acknowledge a significant pitfall: the Dunning-Kruger effect. This cognitive bias describes a phenomenon where individuals with low ability in a specific area tend to overestimate their competence. In essence, they are too unskilled to recognize their own lack of skill. This can lead to a dangerous, unearned confidence—a phenomenon sometimes humorously called the &amp;ldquo;Peak of Mount Stupid.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;The whole problem with the world is that fools and fanatics are always so certain of themselves, and wiser people so full of doubts.&amp;rdquo;
— Bertrand Russell&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>7. The Energetic Blueprint: Frequencies, Mindsets, and Manifestation</title><link>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/07-energetic-blueprint/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/07-energetic-blueprint/</guid><description>&lt;p>Beyond the purely tangible, our internal states—our thoughts, emotions, and beliefs—profoundly influence our physiological responses, cognitive patterns, and behavioral tendencies. This intricate interplay forms a dynamic internal &amp;lsquo;blueprint&amp;rsquo; that shapes how we perceive and interact with the world. Understanding this fundamental principle is key to consciously shaping your reality.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;If you want to find the secrets of the universe, think in terms of energy, frequency and vibration.&amp;rdquo;
— Nikola Tesla&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>8. Emotional Intelligence: Navigating Your Inner World</title><link>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/08-emotional-intelligence/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/08-emotional-intelligence/</guid><description>&lt;p>Beyond models and thinking paradigms, our emotional state plays a pivotal role in our journey. True mastery involves not just intellectual understanding, but also the ability to navigate and leverage our emotions. Emotional awareness is the capacity to recognize and understand our own feelings, as well as those of others. It&amp;rsquo;s about being present with your emotions, rather than suppressing or being overwhelmed by them.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Anyone can be angry – that is easy. But to be angry with the right person, to the right degree, at the right time, for the right purpose, and in the right way – that is not easy.&amp;rdquo;
— Aristotle&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>9. The State of High Performance: Energy, Clarity, and Focus</title><link>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/09-state-of-high-performance/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/09-state-of-high-performance/</guid><description>&lt;p>To truly excel in the &amp;lsquo;Doing&amp;rsquo; phase, it is essential to master your state of being. This goes beyond mere action and delves into the quality of your performance, which hinges on three pillars: Energy, Clarity, and Focus.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First, Energy is the fuel of ambition. High achievement is not sustained by willpower alone, but by vibrant physical and mental energy. This means prioritizing sleep, nutrition, and exercise not as chores, but as critical components of your success architecture. A tired mind cannot think clearly, and a weary body cannot execute with precision. In our analogy, this is ensuring the horse is well-fed, rested, and in peak condition before a long journey.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>10. The Engine of Progress: Discipline, Consistency, and Reflection</title><link>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/10-engine-of-progress/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/10-engine-of-progress/</guid><description>&lt;p>Flow states are powerful, but they are not accidental. They are the result of a deep, underlying structure of discipline and consistency. While focus gets you into the zone, it is discipline that builds the runway for takeoff. Discipline is the conscious choice to do what needs to be done, even when you don&amp;rsquo;t feel like it. It is the bridge between your goals and your accomplishments.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;We are what we repeatedly do. Excellence, then, is not an act, but a habit.&amp;rdquo;
— Will Durant&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>11. The Great Battle: Delayed vs. Instant Gratification</title><link>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/11-delayed-vs-instant-gratification/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/11-delayed-vs-instant-gratification/</guid><description>&lt;p>At the heart of discipline lies a fundamental conflict that every Seeker must master: the battle between instant gratification and delayed gratification. This is the daily struggle between the man and his horse. The horse, driven by instinct, craves immediate pleasure—the sugar cube now, the easy path, the rest in the shade. It operates on the principle of &amp;lsquo;I want it now.&amp;rsquo; The rider, however, understands the map. He knows that indulging every immediate whim of the horse will lead them astray, far from their ultimate destination. He must train the horse to forgo the immediate, lesser pleasure for the greater, future reward.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>12. Thinking Paradigms: Process, Probability, and Beyond Dualism</title><link>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/12-thinking-paradigms/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/12-thinking-paradigms/</guid><description>&lt;p>Our approach to goals is also shaped by how we perceive reality. A crucial distinction lies between process-oriented thinking and outcome-oriented thinking. The Have-Do-Be and Do-Have-Be models are heavily outcome-oriented. The focus is solely on the end result, and if that result isn&amp;rsquo;t achieved, it can lead to disappointment and a sense of failure. This can make the journey feel like a means to an end, rather than a valuable experience in itself.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>13. Navigating Reality: The Power of Mental Models</title><link>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/13-navigating-reality/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/13-navigating-reality/</guid><description>&lt;p>To effectively navigate the complexities of life, the Seeker must cultivate a toolbox of mental models. These are frameworks for thinking that help you simplify and understand the world, allowing you to make better decisions. They are like different maps for different terrains; having a variety of them prevents you from getting lost.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;The map is not the territory.&amp;rdquo;
— Alfred Korzybski&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Here are a few essential models to begin with:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>14. Embracing the Unfair Game: Paradox and Contrarian Thinking</title><link>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/14-embracing-the-unfair-game/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/14-embracing-the-unfair-game/</guid><description>&lt;p>The Seeker must accept a fundamental truth: life is not fair. It is a complex, chaotic, and often paradoxical game. The universe does not distribute talent, opportunity, or luck evenly. To pretend otherwise is to set yourself up for resentment and frustration. The key is not to demand fairness, but to learn to play the hand you are dealt with skill and wisdom.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;The world is not a just place. It is a relentless and amoral arena where the strong, the clever, and the lucky prevail.&amp;rdquo;
— Unknown&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>15. The Be-Do-Have Model: Attracting Your Reality</title><link>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/15-be-do-have-model/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/15-be-do-have-model/</guid><description>&lt;p>The Be-Do-Have model flips the conventional approach on its head and is a powerful framework for sustainable success and fulfillment. It starts with an internal shift:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;The best way to predict the future is to create it.&amp;rdquo;
— Peter Drucker&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h3 id="be">
 BE
 &lt;a class="anchor" href="#be">#&lt;/a>
&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Begin by being the person you need to be to achieve your goals. This involves cultivating the mindset, beliefs, values, and identity of someone who already embodies what they desire. For example, if you aspire to be a successful entrepreneur, start being confident, resourceful, resilient, and innovative right now. This is about internal alignment and self-perception. This internal shift is often rooted in faith or trust (whether in oneself, the universe, or a higher power). It&amp;rsquo;s the belief that by focusing on who you are becoming and taking aligned action, the desired outcomes will manifest. For many, this faith extends to a belief in God, providing a profound sense of peace and assurance that their path is divinely guided, and that challenges are opportunities for growth. In the analogy, this is the rider cultivating an unshakeable belief in his ability to guide the horse, and the horse, sensing this conviction, responds with trust and cooperation.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>16. The Symphony of Success: Harmonizing Internal Fulfillment and External Achievement</title><link>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/16-symphony-of-success/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/16-symphony-of-success/</guid><description>&lt;p>The ultimate aim of the Seeker&amp;rsquo;s journey is not merely external achievement, but a profound sense of internal fulfillment that accompanies and transcends it. The Be-Do-Have model inherently bridges this gap, revealing that true success is a symphony where both internal and external elements play in harmony.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Be-Do-Have model reverses this. By first cultivating your &amp;lsquo;Being&amp;rsquo; – your core identity, values, and purpose – you lay the foundation for authentic action. When your &amp;lsquo;Doing&amp;rsquo; is aligned with this internal truth, the &amp;lsquo;Having&amp;rsquo; that follows is not just a material gain, but a natural extension of your integrated self. This creates a virtuous cycle: external achievements become reflections of your internal growth, and each success reinforces your sense of purpose and fulfillment.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>17. Conclusion: The Edge of Transformation</title><link>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/conclusion-the-edge-of-transformation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://anas1412.github.io/notes/docs/conclusion-the-edge-of-transformation/</guid><description>&lt;p>We have journeyed from the flawed paradigms of Have-Do-Be and Do-Have-Be to the transformative power of the Be-Do-Have model. We have explored the depths of our own psychology, the nature of discipline, and the mental models required for success. But all these lessons circle back to a single, profound truth:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Success without fulfillment is the ultimate failure.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I learned this lesson not in a book, but in the soul-crushing reality of a life I was told I should want. I learned this lesson not in a book, but in the soul-crushing reality of a life I was told I should want. I was in a paid software engineering post-internship, finishing my university years to graduate. I remember the feeling of anticipation, waiting for a salary that felt more like an allowance. I had poured everything into that role: I automated their entire backup system, slashing deployment times by 80%. I streamlined the onboarding process for new developers, cutting it from a week to less than a day. I had worked hard, delivered immense value, and what was my reward? The last three months of my already meager salary went unpaid. The final straw came when the CEO, after a dispute with the sales team, stormed into our office and yelled at me for a trivial issue. In that moment, I was so disappointed and disgusted that I began to hate the very thing I once loved—coding and automation.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>